On Monday, about 270 pilot whales
got into difficulty
on a sand bank at MacQuarie
heads near Strahn on
Tasmania's West coast.
About 190 kilometers
from Hobart.
The Department of
primary industry,
parks, Water and
Environment,
DPIPWE said
the whales were stranded at
three different sites.
Adding, this morning that
about a third had died.
Why do whales
strand themselves?
Dr. Vanessa Pirotta from
Macquarie University said,
it remains a mystery.
Whales use echolocation
to navigate.
They're seeing the world
through clicks and sounds.
She said, Dr Pirotta
said the current event
could be a case
of an individual
or couple leading
the pod and they've
misnavigated
the waterway.
She said the
animals leading
the pod may have
been frightened,
and taken evasive action,
which had led the
group into trouble,
or perhaps a sense of
adventure had led them
astray. maybe
something startled
them or maybe they're
just curious.
Dr. Pirotta said, Nick
Deka from DPIPWE,
said Australia's
southern-most state
was known for mass
whale standings.
Whale strandings
are not uncommon in
Tasmania and
whale strandings,
of this scale are
not uncommon either.
But certainly we haven't
had one for at
least ten years.
He said.